Guide to the James Finley Cavagnaro Railway and locomotive historical societies: album, 1940-1958
Department of Special Collections
Cavagnaro, James Finley, Jr., collector. Railway and locomotive historical societies: album,
1940-1958
M1157
Cavagnaro, James Finley, Jr., collector.
1 linear ft. (1 manuscript box and 1 print box)
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Society newsletters and magazines, rail excursion flyers, excursion photographs, news clippings, announcements, time tables, ticket stubs, map, etc.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Originally a gift to the Hopkins Transportation Library, transferred to Special Collections, 2000.
Historical note
During the 1950s there were several important local organizations devoted to railroad history: The Pacific Coast Railroad and Locomotive Historical Society, Inc., the California-Nevada Railroad Historical Society, the Bay Area Electric Railroad Association, and the Central Railway Club of San Jose. These organizations published regular newsletters and sponsored special excursions. In addition, there were two local monthly magazines dedicated to railroading, the WESTERN RAILROADER and the SOUTHERN PACIFIC BULLETIN.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
Society newsletters and magazines, rail excursion flyers, excursion photographs, news clippings, announcements, time tables, ticket stubs, map, etc.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
DeVee Trucking.; Southern Pacific.; Union Pacific.; Western Pacific.; Sacramento Northern.; Sierra Railroad Company.; Bay Area Electric Railroad Association, Inc.; California-Nevada Railroad Historical Society.; Pacific Coast Railway and Locomotive Society, Inc.; Railroads--California.; Railroads--History--Societies, etc.; Railroads--United States--History.; Albums.; Photoprints.; Hopkins Transportation Library.; Southern Pacific Bulletin.; The Western Railroader.
Collection Contents
- Chapter News, Pacific Coast Railway and Locomotive Society, Inc. Oct, Nov 1951; Jan-Apr, Jul-Sep, Nov, Dec 1952; Jan-Jun, Aug, Oct 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  one letter, 1953.
- Bulletins, California-Nevada Railroad Historical Society. 1941; Nov 1951, Oct-Nov 1952; Oct 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Newsletter, "The Circuit Breaker," Bay Area Electric Railroad Assn. Inc.Apr, Jul, Dec 1952; Apr 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Rail excursion flyers 1941, 1951-1953, 12 sheets (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "The Sonora Express" excursion,Oct 7, 1951, 4 sheets (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "The Hangtown Express" excursionNov 4, 1951, 2 sheets (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "The Big Trees Picnic Train" excursion, Jul 20, 1952. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- The Western Railroader Magazine, "Sonora Express.", Oct 23, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- The Western Railroader Magazine, "Sonora Express.", Mar, Jun, Aug-Nov, 1951). (Box 1, Folder 9)
- The Western Railroader Magazine, "Sonora Express.", Jan-Jun, Aug-Nov 1952 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Includes one booklist.
- The Western Railroader Magazine, "Sonora Express.", Jan-Apr, Oct-Nov 1953 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- The Western Railroader Magazine, "Sonora Express.", Jun 1958 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Southern Pacific Bulletin, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- "Railroading on San Franciso Bay,"Aug 1953, 1 sheet (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Sacramento Northern Inspection Report Forms n.d., 2 sheets (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Western Pacific Train Order ("slow order"), 1952, l sheet (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Announcement, Railroad Exhibit, Stanford University Library 1951, 1 sheet (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Retirement, A. T. Mercier, Pres., Southern Pacific, Jan. 3, 1952., 2 newsclippings (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Announcement, inauguration of the "Santa Fe Chief." [1951] (Box 1, Folder 19)
  1 news clip, with press photo of Fred G. Gurley, Pres. Santa Fe Railway
- Miscellaneous advertisments, flyers, magazine back issue list, tour brochure, pamphlet [ 1953?], 6 items (Box 1, Folder 20)
- DeVee Trucking (California).Mar 13, 1955, 1 newsclipping (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Photo album and scrapbook1946-1953 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Contains photos and memorabilia: "The Sonora Express" excursion, Oct 7, 1951, (pp 6-31) -- "Hang Town Express " excursion, Nov 4, 1951 (pp. 34-63) -- Stanford rail exhibit, 1951, (p.67) -- Keeler, California, [1952?], (pp 69-73) -- Sacramento excursion, Feb 7, 1952, (pp. 75-97) -- Southern Pacific[ 1952?], (pp 99-105) -- Sierra Railroad, [Mar 1952 ?], ( pp 109-111) - Interurban excursion, Apr 6, 1952, (pp. 113-123) -- Santa Fe "San Diegan" enroute along the ocean, 1952 (p. 24) -- unknown location photos, (pp 126-127) -- Oakland, California, to Pittsburgh, California, Jul 6 1952, (pp. 128-132) -- "Big Trees Picnic" excursion, Jul 20, 1952, (pp. 133-135)